ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

SUMMARY

Program Manager and Data Scientist with **7+ years of proven success** establishing and scaling transformative, enterprise–level, AI/ML initiatives across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Led the Data Science team's **63% market share** in AI developments across British Petroleum's US onshore O&G business and independently produced **US\$20MM in annual value**. Delivered **patent–pending** AI solutions in computational chemistry — **valued at US\$500M+ annually** — for INFICON's Semiconductor business.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Program Manager

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present Denver. Colorado

- · Directed and executed strategy for BP US onshore Data Science and ML Engineering achieving 47% market share in Exploration & Development and enabling the team's 63% market share across the division.
- · Managed and deployed the Long-term Production Risk Assessment Simulation tool for Reservoir Engineering.
- · Oversaw the AWS migration for PowerBI reports monitoring the Productivity Index and Saltwater Disposal.

Senior Data Scientist

British Petroleum (BP)

February 2023 – Present

Denver, Colorado

- · Generated US\$20MM annually in value for Reservoir Engineering's EOR initiatives delivering the ML Refracturing Estimator and increasing confidence in the Business Unit's Development program by 500%.
- · Launched ML Lithology Recognition for unconventional reservoirs in partnership with Subsurface Technology expected to yield US\$5.5MM annually in the Bone Spring and Wolfcamp formations.

Data Scientist

INFICON

June 2018 – February 2023 Syracuse, New York

- Directed the Automated Sensor Calibration development program for semiconductor sensor technologies —
 delivering patent—pending advances driving annual cost reductions forecasted in excess of US\$500M.
- · Invented the Bijective Neural Architecture for density estimation yielding a 95% increase in accuracy.
- · Led efforts defining mathematical foundations for signal processing algorithms and designed A/B tests using SciPy.stats and Nolds delivering a 21% increase in sensor fidelity using SciPy.optimize and Statsmodels.
- · Established KPIs and executed A/B tests with simulated chemical data via PySwarms, SciPy.optimize, SciPy.stats, and SciPy.integrate attaining 50% coverage across chemical detection/monitoring systems.

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors

U.S. Patent and Trademark Office

August 2022
Patent Pending

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Core Analysis Workshop

UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology

April 2024/December 2023

Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX

Havens Consulting

April 2023

Power BI — Reporting and Model Building February 2023 Havens Consulting Machine Learning for Model Predictive Control & Process Analytics June 2019 Dr. S. Joe Qin INVITED PRESENTATIONS November 2020 Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity INFICON Data Analytics Summit Introduction to AI and Machine Learning November 2020 INFICON Data Analytics Summit Automatic Text Summarization — Deep Learning & Classical Approaches April 2018 Syracuse University iSchool Poster Session Characterizing Popularity Growth for Social Media Content August 2017 Electrical Engineering & Computer Science REU Seminar HONORS & AWARDS August 2017 - May 2018 Graduate Merit Scholarship Syracuse University Summa Cum Laude May 2017 Syracuse University The Warren Semon Prize May 2017 Syracuse University Dean's Leadership Grant September 2014 Syracuse University Dean's List August 2014 - May 2017Syracuse University The Founders' Scholarship August 2014 - May 2017 Syracuse University

EDUCATION

Syracuse University May 2018

Master of Science | Computer Science

Syracuse University
Bachelor of Science | Computer Science
Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Software & Tools AWS SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Statsmodels, Pandas,

SciPy, NumPy, NLTK, Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog

Competency Areas AI, Deep Learning, Machine/Statistical Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling, Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Time Series, Statistical Signal Processing, Data Analysis, Data Mining, Agile, CRISP-DM